Guide to the Stanford Technology Ventures Program, Entrepreneurial Thought Leaders Seminar, Videorecordings SC1209
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Technology Ventures Program, Entrepreneurial Thought Leaders Seminar, videorecordings
2001-2014
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University. Stanford Technology Ventures Program.
SC1209
391966.72 megabyte(s)
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Biographical/Historical note
The Stanford Technology Ventures Program (STVP) is the entrepreneurship center at Stanford University's School of Engineering. Hosted by the department of Management Science and Engineering, STVP is dedicated to accelerating high-technology entrepreneurship education and creating scholarly research on technology-based firms that, in turn, provides new insights for students, scholars, and business leaders.
STVP provides undergraduate and graduate students from all majors with the entrepreneurial skills needed to use innovations to solve major world problems, with an emphasis on the environment, human health, information technology, and other global issues. Research efforts tackle the challenges of creating successful ventures and innovative large firms, and then taking that knowledge to the classroom and publication. Their global outreach program includes annual conferences on several continents and a website that includes thousands of video clips and podcasts regarding technology entrepreneurship and innovation. They strive to create new ideas, and inspire and prepare students to be leaders in existing organizations, new ventures, and academia.
The Draper Fisher Jurvetson (DFJ) Entrepreneurial Thought Leaders (ETL) Seminar is a weekly lecture series on entrepreneurship featuring entrepreneurs, innovators and industry leaders. Stanford students can earn credit for attending the series by registering for MS&E 472. The series is also free and open to the public.
Examples of past speakers include:
Founders of: Google, Facebook, AOL, JetBlue, Instagram, Yahoo!, LinkedIn, Twitter and Zynga
Venture capitalists: John Doerr, Steve Jurvetson, Vinod Khosla, Mark Suster and Brad Feld
Executives from market leaders: Cisco, Electronic Arts, HP, NVIDIA, Genentech, Microsoft and Amazon
Social entrepreneurs from: The Global Fund for Women, Conservation International, Teach for America and Nika Water
Leading voices on high-tech entrepreneurship: Geoffrey Moore, Guy Kawasaki, Reid Hoffman and Steve Blank
Technology -- Social aspects -- Study and teaching; Technology -- social aspects.; High technology industries -- California; High technology -- Research.; High technology industries -- California -- Santa Clara County.; Stanford University. Stanford Technology Ventures Program.
- Videorecordings, 2001-2014
  - Bartz, Carol, Entrepreneurship in Established Companies, 2001-10-24; 1; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bartz, Carol, president and CEO of Autodesk, Inc., argues that entrepreneurship is more important in large companies. The companies that survive do so because they know how to innovate, take risks, and reward risk-taking organizational behavior and structure.
  - Bartz, Carol, Fail Fast Forward: Appreciating Risk, 2001-10-24; 2; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bartz talks about a slogan inside Autodesk called fail fast forward to counter a fear of failure within an established organization. Their goal was to have employees understand that failure is very acceptable within an established organization--the key is to identify it quickly, and move forward with lessons learned. This is an attempt to break free from those who are worried about risk-taking.
  - Bartz, Carol, The Importance of Attitude, 2001-10-24; 3; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    What kind of attitude do you bring into a situation? Are you willing to change and take risks? Bartz reminisces about a team member with a negative attitude and explains how she looks for go-getter attitudes in finding new team members.
  - Bartz, Carol, Managing Cycles, 2001-10-24; 4; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bartz shares her view on the concept of cycles. She challenges entrepreneurs to manage cycles in their personal life, professional life, and within product cycles and the market.
  - Bartz, Carol, Learning About Yourself, 2001-10-24; 5; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bartz argues that you should learn how to pick your self up, be scared and cover it up, or be emotional and show it at different points in your life. The younger you learn, the better off you are. Do not be something you are not, she says, learn who you really are.
  - Bartz, Carol, Who Should You Surround Yourself With?, 2001-10-24; 6; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bartz stresses the importance of surrounding yourself with good people. Some of the best leaders in the land, she notes, are adamant about surrounding themselves with good people.
  - Bartz, Carol, It's About Loving What You Do., 2001-10-24; 7; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bartz passion for programming is not about making money; it is about loving what she is doing. Whatever it is your doing, she says, make sure it is something you enjoy. The best leaders who are entrepreneurs are doing what they like.
  - Bartz, Carol, The personal Side of Management, 2001-10-24; 8; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bartz believes you will spend more time at work than in personal activities. If you are in management, one of your responsibilities is to make sure you care for your employees with compassion and interest in their lives.
  - Bartz, Carol, Trust and Honesty at the Work Place, 2001-10-24; 9; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bartz explains that the way to earn her trust is to be blatantly honest. It is hard to unravel a situation if it has been covered up. For this reason, she looks to people who admit their mistakes.
  - Bartz, Carol, Moving Laterally in a Company, 2001-10-24; 10; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bartz argues that you must understand how a company is run. Life is about horizontal and lateral moves. She also talks about the various positions she has held in the past, from analyst to VP of customer service. By the time she became CEO, she had acquired a strong background in various fields.
  - Bartz, Carol, Autodesk and the Wireless Industry, 2001-10-24; 11; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Autodesk's vision is to keep the design data in digital format. Wireless industry is essential in this area. A small team of engineers at Autodesk banded together and built a wireless product on the fly to address an immediate need.
  - Bartz, Carol, Managing a Balanced Life, 2001-10-24; 12; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bartz examines long-term balance and encourages people to catch themselves before they fall too far. Learn how to manage the various activities you are involved in, she says. Juggling is pertinent to career development.
  - Bartz, Carol, Moving Forward and Changing Processes, 2001-10-24; 13; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Over the last three years, Autodesk had to change delivery times due to customers' faster delivery demand. Autodesk was able to move forward using software as service, thinking about process, and innovating in an established company.
  - Bartz, Carol, The Concept Behind Buzzsaw.com, 2001-10-24; 14; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bartz discusses Buzzsaw.com, a company created to provide a hosted environment for the construction industry. Because Autodesk had no experience in the construction industry, the company spun out Buzzsaw and then bought it back after a successful fundraising round with VCs.
  - Bartz, Carol, Promoting Quality Leaders from Within, 2001-10-24; 15; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    How do you seek out and promote quality leaders from within a company? Leaders are often self-selected from peers, Bartz says. On way to identify them is to set up a management meeting and tap into the different groups across the company and note who gets picked to represent the individual groups. Usually, these are your leaders. Because they are easy to work with and are creative, they are sought out as leaders at whatever level they are in. No one wants to work with an asshole, however qualified they may be.
  - Bartz, Carol, Learning From Failure, 2001-10-24; 16; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bartz talks about how people who failed within Buzzsaw, were often given new projects to work on. Failure was valued, she says. Rather than criticizing projects that failed, Bartz notes how people wanted to apply the knowledge they learned from mistakes into new projects.
  - Bartz, Carol, Lateral Moves Within Companies, 2001-10-24; 17; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    How do you take a task that you already know how to do and do it a whole different way? Bartz talks about lateral moves within companies to improve innovation. She looks forward to future technology that will allow the creation of rich media content.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Bit by the Entrepreneurship Bug, 2002-04-24; 18; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khosla, Vinod, partner at Kleiner, Perkins, Caufield & Byers, was bitten by the entrepreneurship bug early in life when he heard about Intel starting up. He was enamored by the idea of being able to start your own company. Intel served as as a great role model, he says.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Career: Learning from Failure Early On, 2002-04-24; 19; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khosla talks about his early career development. He first tried to do a company in India based on milk from soybeans. He travelled to Carnegie Mellon, and then to Stanford University. He describes why persistence and evangelism are important. Although he was not admitted to Stanford at first, saught more real-world experience, and was not admitted again, through persuasion and persistence, he was finally accepted.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Taking Risks, 2002-04-24; 20; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Launching a start-up is not a rational act. And Khosla, Vinod, a partner in Kleiner, Perkins, Caufield & Byers and former Sun Microsystems CEO, believes that success only comes from those who are foolish enough to think unreasonably. Entrepreneurs need to stretch themselves beyond convention and constraint to reach something extraordinary.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Build a Company to Change the World, 2002-04-24; 21; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khosla never intended to be a venture capitalist and still doesn't consider himself as one. He considers himself a venture assistant who has little interest in business other than its necessity for economics and its power to change the world. Khosla loves technology and believes that it drives most of the change that happen in the world.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Company Building to Change the World, 2002-04-24; 22; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Entrepreneurs are far less successful when they are trying to make money--they are much more successful when they have a mission to change the world. No matter what you do, Khosla says, you have to be foolish to do what an entrepreneur attempts. Whatever your value proposition is, it should have the goal of making the world a better place and you should feel passionately about your contribution. If you don't have this and you run into an obstacle, you get stuck. If you are passionate about your product and your message, you can power through problems more easily.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Role of VC in Valuation, 2002-04-24; 23; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Things aren't ever as good or as bad as we think. Today (2002) is one of the best environments to be an investor. The last three or four years were not a lot of fun--if Khosla went to someone to build a reasonable business, the response he would get was that another company was willing to give more money for less work. He would have to explain that the role of a VC was to help companies develop a real economic model and to give an honest valuation.
  - Khosla, Vinod, When You Don't Know What You Don't Know, 2002-04-24; 24; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Where most entrepreneurs fail is on the things they don't know, Khosla says. The biggest problem is when you don't know what you don't know!
  - Khosla, Vinod, Khosla, Vinod: Envisioning the Future, 2002-04-24; 25; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    When things are hot, that's not the area to invest, Khosla cautions. There is a surprise element always present where the biggest opportunities lie. Khosla highlights his interests in biology, genetics, nanotechnology and optical technology.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Any Big Problem is a Big Opportunity, 2002-04-24; 26; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khosla states that any big problem is a big opportunity. If there is no problem, there is no solution, and no reason for a company to exist. No one will pay you to solve a a problem that doesn't exist, he explains.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Think Big and Act Small, 2002-04-24; 27; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khosla explains how to think big and act small. He reminds us that part of that process must be done on a belief system. Without a mission or belief system about how to change the world, one will not be successful.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Technology as Driver of Change, 2002-04-24; 28; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khosla shares his view on technology-driven entrepreneurship and predicts the growing impact of technology on life, society, and the economy.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Social Entrepreneurship, 2002-04-24; 29; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    In Kleiner Perkins perspective, Khosla argues, the traditional model of giving is broken. Social entrepreneurship and ways to leverage money are very important. Although there is not enough money in the world to solve the world's problems, if you apply and multiply, there are, in fact, solutions to some of these problems. Examples of companies providing these solutions include Gramine Bank and Aprotech.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Strength of a Team, 2002-04-24; 30; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khosla states that it is the team that make the company. At Kleiner Perkins, he notes that everyone has learned much from each other. personalities and approaches are diverse and combined to create great strength.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Juniper Networks: Customer Feedback, 2002-04-24; 32; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khosla talks about how Juniper Networks started, and the role of customer feedback in the product development. There was not one vendor thinking of building an OC48 router for the internet. Juniper perservered and took a risk in the technology, despite the majority of customer feedback.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Entrepreneurship is the Driving Engine of the Economy, 2002-04-24; 33; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khosla believes that entrepreneurship is the driving engine of the economy. Don't give up on your dream, he says, -entrepreneurship is a passion. Follow your passions and interests!
  - Khosla, Vinod, Cycles of Fear and Greed, 2002-04-24; 34; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khosla claims that investors only have two emotions: fear and greed. He has seen the trend of investing, which bounces between cycles of fear and cycles of greed.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Career Development: Go Deep, 2002-04-24; 35; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    It is important to use time to get deep expertise, Khosla notes. You need to go much deeper in understanding technology--a bachelor's degree is not enough and will be irrelevant in another 10 years. If you have a goal of entrepreneurship in mind, you must go deep in an expertise in order to advance your career.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Right Time to Build the Team, 2002-04-24; 36; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    From an entrepreneurs point of view, it is a great time (2002) to assemble a team that isn't distracted by money, and is interested in building a real team, and developing a solid business plan.
  - Khosla, Vinod, Great CEOs Build Great Teams, 2002-04-24; 37; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Great CEOs are people who put great teams together. Kriens, Scott at Juniper is one of the best CEOs Khosla has ever worked with, as well as Bill Campbell. There isn't always one definition of a CEO, Khosla notes, each situation requires a different kind of leader, and each stage of a company has different needs for that leader.
  - Khosla, Vinod, To Get an MBA, or Not?, 2002-04-24; 38; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khosla feels that an MBA is not the only way to gain experience, it is a way to gain perspective. Real-world experience provides the depth of knowledge you need in a company.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, What is an Entrepreneur?, 2002-10-23; 39; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hawkins, Jeff, co-founder of Handspring, has never thought of himself as an entrepreneur.Being an entrepreneur is not a career choice, he says, but is something you do at certain points in your life because you have to. Hawkins believes entrepreneurship is a means to an end, as opposed to an end in itself.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Genesis of Palm Computing, 2002-10-23; 40; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hawkins talks about his life, his education and work experience. He started his career at Intel for 3 years and then moved to a start-up that he did not start. While working at the latter he created his first product - first pen-based computer. He soon realised that all personal computing ought to be smaller and simpler. With this thought he started on the path to try and accelerate this shift - and that was the genesis of Palm computing.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, The Accidental Entrepreneur: Palm History, 2002-10-23; 41; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hawkins never really wanted to start a company, he admits. He considers himself an accidental entrepreneur who was approached by two venture capitalists while planning on building a small product.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Story of Acquisition: Palm, US Robotics, 3Com, 2002-10-23; 42; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hawkins shares his story about how his initial company was continually acquired by larger companies.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Spinoff: Handspring, 2002-10-23; 43; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hawkins shares the various reasons why he and his team finally spun off from 3Com to start Handspring. Although they were reluctant to leave and start a company from scratch, they felt that Palm did not belong in 3Com- a networking company. Palm was the only healthy division in 3Com and they could not continue growing and competing with a financial hand tied behind their backs.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Handspring: Envisioning the Future, 2002-10-23; 44; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hawkins discusses how the cell phone took over mobile devices in the realm of personal computing. He projects where Handspring will go in the future with this transition.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Serial Entrepreneurship: Redwood Neuroscience Institute, 2002-10-23; 45; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hawkins is working on his third start-up. Besides starting Palm and Handspring, Hawkins also followed his passion for theoretical neuroscience, the study of how certain parts of the brain work from an information theory point of view. He started a non-profit research institute called the Redwood NeuroScience Institute. Through this experience, he learned that starting a non-profit is just like starting a business.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Profiles of Entrepreneurs, 2002-10-23; 46; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hawkins does not believe there is a single model for an entrepreneur. Each entrepreneur is unique in their own way, he says.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Importance of Experience, 2002-10-23; 47; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    It helps to have experience under your belt before you start your own business, says Hawkins. You ought to have experience working for a good management team and give yourself time to have great mentors. You also have to learn to manage growth and success and how to deal with and anticipate bad times. In Hawkin's experience, the vast majority of people that start companies and do so successfully have had past experiences that helped them.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Follow Your Passions, 2002-10-23; 48; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hawkins, Jeff encourages students to do something they believe in. Business is hard and every company will have its trouble, the only way one gets through these times is if they you a cause and you believe in it. This passion gives momentum to see the bad times through. In his experience, people who started a company for the sake of starting a company failed when the hard times came upon them. At Palm the passion was the product, selling the company was not in contradiction with this passion, but allowed people at Palm to continue making good products. He says that it doesn't matter that the money isn't rolling in, but that we are all excited about what we are doing, and we think its great! This excitement carries companies and people through!
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Individual vs. Company, 2002-10-23; 49; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hawkins stresses that one must separate oneself from work. You are not your company, he says, you are not your product. Your company may fail, your product may fail, but not you, he adds. He stresses the importance of giving credit where it is due.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Entrepreneurship is a Means to an End, 2002-10-23; 50; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Entrepreneurship is a means to an end, it is not an end in itself. The passion is with the product, Hawkins notes, and succesful entrepreneurs must follow it through.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, You Can Live a Normal Life, 2002-10-23; 51; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    According to Hawkins, no one remembers the 14 hours at work or the time missed with their kids. What people remember is if they changed the world, if they had a good time in the process, or if they promoted a positive culture. He talks about balance in regards to developing a great product and having a normal life. Hawkins believes that you can do it all and live a normal life!
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Defining Company Culture, 2002-10-23; 52; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hawkins believes you have to be conscious and methodological about your company culture. The culture starts at the top and permeates to the bottom. The culture at palm is a product culture. High integrity is not just internal, but integrity with vendors, suppliers and customers. A lot of companies keep secrets, but the transparency has been very good for Palm, Hawkins points out. A good, solid culture can help a company go through hard times.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Difficult Negotiations, 2002-10-23; 53; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hawkins talks about the complicated negotiations with 3COM for the spin off of Palm. Discussions lasted five months and involved investment bankers and board members. Five different proposals were presented to the CEO, including spinning off Palm two years in the future. However, the final decision involved no doors banging, and no storming out of offices. All said and done, Hawkins, Jeff did not want to start a company.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Designing Successful Products, 2002-10-23; 54; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hawkins, Jeff, one of the founders of Handspring, claims to have witnessed teams of entrepreneurs brainstorming a product just for the sake of the sale, and he criticizes this approach. A good product can only be conjured by a genuine need in the marketplace. If there are no holes to fill, says Hawkins, then there is no point to being an entrepreneur.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, The Role of Market Research, 2002-10-23; 55; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Founder of the Palm Hawkins, Jeff shares his story of graffiti, a handwriting recognition software, and the intuitive leap of using a keyboard to show that users can and will adopt to new technology. He elaborates on the role of market research, as well as how to listen to customers and follow your intuition and vision for the future.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Work/Life Balance, 2002-10-23; 56; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)